What if our plants
ماذا لو كانت النباتات
could sense the toxicity levels in the soil
لديها القدرة على الإحساس بدرجة السموم في التربة
and express that toxicity through the color of its leaves?
وأظهرت نسبة السُّميَّة عبر لون أوراقها؟
What if those plants could also remove those toxins from the soil?
ماذا لوأزالت تلك النباتات هذه السموم من التربة؟
Instead, what if those plants
بدلََا من ذلك، ماذا لو أن تلك النباتات
grew their own packaging,
أنمت التغليف الخاص بها،
or were designed to only be harvested
أو صُممت ليحصدها فقط
by their owners' own patented machines?
أصحابها باستخدام آلاتهم المسجَّلة؟
What happens when biological design
ماذا يحدث عندما يكون التصميم البيولوجي
is driven by the motivations of mass-produced commodities?
منساقًا لحوافز السلع المنتَجة على نطاق واسع؟
What kind of world would that be?
ما حال العالم بهذا الشكل؟
My name is Ani, and I'm a designer and researcher at MIT Media Lab,
أدعى (آني) وأعمل مصممة وباحثة في مختبر الوسائط MIT ،
where I'm part of a relatively new and unique group called Design Fiction,
وعضو في مجموعة جديدة وفريدة نسبيََا تسمى الخيال التصميمي،
where we're wedged somewhere between science fiction and science fact.
حيث نقع في مكان بين الخيال العلمي والحقيقة العلمية.
And at MIT, I am lucky enough to rub shoulders with scientists
وفيMIT، يحالفني الحظ لأن أختلط بعلماء
studying all kinds of cutting edge fields
يدرسون جميع أنواع المجالات الرائدة
like synthetic neurobiology,
مثل علم الأعصاب الصناعية،
artificial intelligence, artificial life
والذكاء الاصطناعي والحياة الاصطناعية
and everything in between.
وكل شيء بين الواقع والخيال.
And across campus, there's truly brilliant scientists
وفي جنبات الحرم الجامعي، يوجد بحق علماء بارعين
asking questions like, "How can I make the world a better place?"
يطرحون أسئلة مثل "كيف أجعل العالم مكانًا أفضل؟"
And part of what my group likes to ask is, "What is better?"
وجزء من مجموعتي يسألون:"ما الأفضل؟"
What is better for you, for me,
ما الأفضل لك ولي،
for a white woman, a gay man,
للمرأة البيضاء والرجل،
a veteran, a child with a prosthetic?
للمخضرم والطفل ذو الأعضاء الصناعية؟
Technology is never neutral.
التكنولوجيا ليست حيادية إطلاقََا.
It frames a reality
فهي تحاكي الواقع
and reflects a context.
وتعكس البيئة.
Can you imagine what it would say about the work-life balance at your office
هل تتخيل ما قد تقوله عن التوازن في الحياة العملية في مكتبك
if these were standard issue on the first day?
إذا كانت هذه الأمور أساسية في أول يوم عمل؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I believe it's the role of artists and designers
أعتقد أنه دور الفنانين والمصممين
to raise critical questions.
لإثارة الأسئلة المعقدة.
Art is how you can see and feel the future,
الفن يكمن في رؤية المستقبل والشعور به،
and today is an exciting time to be a designer,
واليوم هو توقيت مثير لتكون مصممََا،
for all the new tools becoming accessible.
لتوفر جميع الأدوات في متناول اليد.
For instance, synthetic biology
فمثلا، علم الأحياء الاصطناعية
seeks to write biology as a design problem.
يسعى لصياغة الأحياء على أنها مشكلة تصميم.
And through these developments,
وخلال هذه التطورات،
my lab asks, what are the roles and responsibilities
تساءل مختبري، ماهي القواعد والمسئوليات التي تقع على عاتق
of an artist, designer, scientist or businessman?
الفنان أو المصمم أوالعالِم أو رجل الأعمال؟
What are the implications
ما هي نتائج
of synthetic biology, genetic engineering,
علم الأحياء الاصطناعية والهندسة الوراثية،
and how are they shaping our notions of what it means to be a human?
وكيف يساهمون في قولبة أفكارنا عن ما هو منسوب للإنسان؟
What are the implications of this on society, on evolution
ما هي نتائج هذا على المجتمع وعلى التطور
and what are the stakes in this game?
وما هي المخاطرة في هذه اللعبة؟
My own speculative design research at the current moment
يقوم بحثي عن التصميم التأمّلي في الوقت الحالي
plays with synthetic biology,
بالعمل مع الأحياء الاصطناعية،
but for more emotionally driven output.
لكن سعيًا وراء نتيجة عاطفية أكثر.
I'm obsessed with olfaction as a design space,
أشعر بالهوس تجاه إدراج حاسة الشم في مجال التصميم،
and this project started with this idea
وبدأ هذا المشروع بهذه الفكرة
of what if you could take a smell selfie, a smelfie?
عن ماذا لو التقطت صورة سيلفي تعبر عن رائحة، سميلفي؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
What if you could take your own natural body odor
ماذا لو تمكنت من أخذ رائحة طبيعية منك
and send it to a lover?
وترسلها لمحبّ؟
Funny enough, I found that this was a 19th century Austrian tradition,
والغريب أني اكتشفت أن هذا هو التقليد النمساوي في القرن 19،
where couples in courtship would keep a slice of apple
حيث كان يتودد الأزواج بإبقاء شريحة من ثمرة التفاح
crammed under their armpit during dances,
مضغوطة تحت الإبط أثناء الرقص،
and at the end of the evening,
وفي نهاية الأمسية،
the girl would give the guy she most fancied her used fruit,
تعطي الفتاة للشاب الذي أعجبت به الفاكهة المستعملة خاصتها،
and if the feeling was mutual,
وإذا كان يبادلها الشعور،
he would wolf down that stinky apple.
يقوم بالتهام تلك القطعة الكريهة،
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Famously, Napoleon wrote many love letters to Josephine,
علي نحو معروف، كتب نابليون العديد من رسائل الحب لجوزفين،
but perhaps amongst the most memorable is this brief and urgent note:
لكن ربما أبرزها هذه الرسالة المختصرة والعاجلة:
"Home in three days. Don't bathe."
"سأعود في غضون ثلاثة أيام. لا تستحم."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Both Napoleon and Josephine adored violets.
أحب نابليون وجوزفين البنفسج حبََا جمََا.
Josephine wore violet-scented perfume,
وضعت جوزفين عطرََا تفوح منه رائحة البنفسج،
carried violets on their wedding day,
وحملوا أزهار البنفسج في يوم زفافهم،
and Napoleon sent her a bouquet of violets
وأرسل لها نابليون باقة ورود من البنفسج
every year on their anniversary.
في ذكري زواجهم كل سنة.
When Josephine passed away,
عندما قَضَت جوزفين نَحْبَها،
he planted violets at her grave,
زرع البنفسج عند قبرها،
and just before his exile,
وقبل منفاه،
he went back to that tomb site,
عاد إلى ذاك الضريح،
picked some of those flowers, entombed them in a locket
وقطف بعضًا من هذه الورود، ودفنهم في قلادة
and wore them until the day he died.
وطوقها حول عنقه إلى أن وافته المنية.
And I found this so moving,
ووجدتُ هذا مؤثرََا بشدة،
I thought, could I engineer that violet to smell just like Josephine?
فكرت، هل أستطيع أن أصمم البنفسج ليشبه في عبيره جوزفين؟
What if, for the rest of eternity,
ماذا لو، إلى الأزل،
when you went to visit her site,
كلما ذهبت لزيارة قبرها،
you could smell Josephine just as Napoleon loved her?
استطعت شم رائحة جوزفين كما أحبها نابليون؟
Could we engineer new ways of mourning,
هل نستطيع تصميم طرق حداد جديدة،
new rituals for remembering?
وطقوس جديدة لاستعادة الذكريات؟
After all, we've engineered transgenic crops
في النهاية قمنا بتصميم محاصيل محوَّلة وراثيََا
to be maximized for profit,
لتحقق الحد الأقصى من الربح،
crops that stand up to transport,
محاصيل تتحمل النقل،
crops that have a long shelf life,
محاصيل تبقي طويلا على الرف،
crops that taste sugary sweet but resist pests,
محاصيل مذاقها حلو لكن تقاوم الآفات،
sometimes at the expense of nutritional value.
أحيانا على حساب القيمة الغذائية.
Can we harness these same technologies for an emotionally sensitive output?
هل نستطيع التحكم في هذه التكنولوجيا للحصول على نتيجة عاطفية؟
So currently in my lab,
لهذا في مختبري حاليًا،
I'm researching questions like, what makes a human smell like a human?
أبحث عن أسئلة مثل، ما الذي يجعل رائحة الإنسان تعبر عنه؟
And it turns out it's fairly complicated.
واتضح أنه سؤال معقد.
Factors such as your diet, your medications, your lifestyle
عوامل مثل نظامك الغذائي والأدوية و أسلوب حياتك
all factor into the way you smell.
جميعها يميّز رائحتك.
And I found that our sweat is mostly odorless,
واكتشفت أن العَرَق ليس له رائحة،
but it's our bacteria and microbiome
لكن البكتيريا والميكروبيوم الخاص بنا
that's responsible for your smells, your mood, your identity
هي المسئولة عن ظهور الرائحة وتغير مزاجك وتحديد هويتك
and so much beyond.
والكثير وراء هذا.
And there's all kinds of molecules that you emit
ويوجد جميع أنواع الجزيئات التي تبعثها
but which we only perceive subconsciously.
لكننا فقط ندركها لاشعوريًا
So I've been cataloging and collecting
كنت أقوم بعمل نماذج وحساب
bacteria from different sites of my body.
عدد البكتريا من أماكن مختلفة في بدني.
After talking to a scientist, we thought,
بعد الانتهاء من حديث مع عالم، اعتقدنا،
maybe the perfect concoction of Ani
أن ربما التواصل المثالي لـ(آني)
is like 10 percent collarbone, 30 percent underarm,
هو بمقدار 10 بالمئة عظم الترقوة و30 بالمئة تحت الذراع،
40 percent bikini line and so forth,
40 بالمئة خط بكيني وهكذا،
and occasionally I let researchers from other labs
وعادةََ أدع الباحثين من معامل أخرى
take a sniff of my samples.
يتنشقوا روائح من عيناتي.
And it's been interesting to hear how smell of the body
ومن المشوق سماع كيف أن رائحة الجسم
is perceived outside of the context of the body.
تدرَك خارج بيئة الجسم.
I've gotten feedback such as,
تلقيت تعليقات مثل أن،
smells like flowers, like chicken,
شذاها مثل الورود، مثل الدجاج،
like cornflakes,
مثل رقائق الذرة،
like beef carnitas.
مثل كرات اللحم،
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
At the same time, I cultivate a set of carnivorous plants
في الوقت ذاته، زرعت مجموعة من النباتات المفترسة
for their ability to emit fleshlike odors to attract prey,
لقدرتها على نشر روائح آدمية لجذب الفريسة،
in an attempt to kind of create this symbiotic relationship
في محاولة لإيجاد علاقة تكافلية
between my bacteria and this organism.
بين البكتريا الخاصة بي وهذا الكائن الحي.
And as it so happens, I'm at MIT and I'm in a bar,
وكما حدث هذا، أنا أعمل في MIT و ذهبت إلى حانة،
and I was talking to a scientist
وكنت أتحدث إلى عالِم
who happens to be a chemist and a plant scientist,
الذي صدف أنه عالم في الكيمياء والنبات
and I was telling him about my project,
وكنت أخبره عن مشروعي،
and he was like, "Well, this sounds like botany for lonely women."
وكان رد فعله مثل، "حسنا، هذا يبدو مثل علم النبات لامرأة وحيدة."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Unperturbed, I said, "OK."
قلت برباطة جأش،"حسنا."
I challenged him.
وقمت بتحدِّيه
"Can we engineer a plant that can love me back?"
"هل نستطيع تصميم نبات قادر على حبي؟"
And for some reason, he was like, "Sure, why not?"
ولسبب ما قال، "طبعًا، لم لا؟"
So we started with, can we get a plant to grow towards me
لذا بدأنا بطرح سؤال، هل نستطيع الحصول على نبات ينمو باتجاهي
like I was the sun?
كما لو كنت الشمس؟
And so we're looking at mechanisms in plants such as phototropism,
وبالتالي ننظر إلى آليات عمل النبات مثل ظاهرة الانتحاء الضوئي،
which causes the plant to grow towards the sun
التي ينتج عنها نمو النبات باتجاه الضوء
by producing hormones like auxin,
بواسطة إنتاج هرمون الأوكسين،
which causes cell elongation on the shady side.
الذي يتسبب في استطالة الخلية في الجزء الظليل.
And right now I'm creating a set of lipsticks
وأعمل الآن على إنتاج مجموعة أحمر شفاه
that are infused with these chemicals
التي تُنقع في هذه المواد الكيميائية
that allow me to interact with a plant on its own chemical signatures --
مما يسمح لي بالتفاعل مع النبات على أساس بصمته الكيميائية --
lipsticks that cause plants to grow where I kiss it,
أحمر شفاه يجعل النباتات تنمو حيث أقبلها،
plants that blossom where I kiss the bloom.
نباتات تتفتح حيث أقبل الزهرة.
And through these projects,
وخلال هذه المشروعات،
I'm asking questions like,
أطرح سؤال مثل،
how do we define nature?
كيف نعرِّف الطبيعة؟
How do we define nature when we can reengineer its properties,
كيف نعرّفها بينما نستطيع إعادة تصميم خصائصها،
and when should we do it?
ومتى يجب أن نقوم بذلك؟
Should we do it for profit, for utility?
هل ينبغي لنا أن نفعله لأجل الربح، لأجل الفائدة؟
Can we do it for emotional ends?
هل نستطيع فعله لغايات عاطفية؟
Can biotechnology be used to create work as moving as music?
هل تُستخدم التكنولوجيا الحيوية لإنتاج عمل مؤثر كالموسيقى؟
What are the thresholds between science
ما هي العتبات بين العلم
and its ability to shape our emotional landscape?
وقدرته على تشكيل صور الطبيعة الوجدانية الخاصة بنا؟
It's a famous design mantra that form follows function.
هذا شعار معروف في التصميم أن الشكل يتبع الوظيفة.
Well, now, wedged somewhere between science, design and art
حسنا، الآن، في مكان يجمع بين العلم والتصميم والفن
I get to ask,
كان علي أن أسأل،
what if fiction informs fact?
ماذا لو شكّل الخيالُ الواقع؟
What kind of R&amp;D lab would that look like
ما هو شكل معمل البحث والتطوير
and what kind of questions would we ask together?
و ما نوع الأسئلة التي نطرحها سويا؟
We often look to technology as the answer,
نحن نتطلع إلى التكنولوجيا كجواب،
but as an artist and designer,
لكن بصفتي فنانة ومصممة،
I like to ask, but what is the question?
أحب أن أسأل، لكن ما هو السؤال؟
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)